<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The custumers apology That is to say, a generall answere to informers of all sortes, and their iniurious complaints, against the honest reputation of the collectors of her Maiesties custumes, specially in the out-portes of this realme. Written onely for vnderstanding readers and wise in highest authoritie, to reade and discerne by. Alwaies prouided, in reading reade all, or nothing at all.</title>
            <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17928</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836594</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836594</idno>
            <idno type="VID">877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07549)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 421:01, 1178:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The custumers apology That is to say, a generall answere to informers of all sortes, and their iniurious complaints, against the honest reputation of the collectors of her Maiesties custumes, specially in the out-portes of this realme. Written onely for vnderstanding readers and wise in highest authoritie, to reade and discerne by. Alwaies prouided, in reading reade all, or nothing at all.</title>
                  <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Roberts,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Milles.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The state of the custumes. Specially in the out-portes of the realme.</note>
                  <note>Only 50 copies were printed; all copies known are signed by the author, and most are dated by hand "1599".</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17929+ on UMI microfilm reel 421, and as STC 17929++ on reel 1178.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reels 421 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and 1178 (Bodleian Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Customs administration --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:877:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:877:1"/>
            <p>THE CVSTVMERS APOLOGY.</p>
            <p>That is to ſay, A generall Anſwere to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers of all ſortes, and their iniurious <hi>complaints, againſt the honeſt reputation</hi> of the Collectors of her Maieſties CVSTVMES, ſpecially in the OVT-PORTES of this Realme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written onely</hi> FOR VNDERSTANDING READERS AND WISE IN HIGHEST AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THORITIE, <hi>to Reade and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne by.</hi> Alwaies prouided, In reading Reade all, or nothing at all.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Natura poteſt <hi>Iuſto</hi> ſecer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere <hi>Iniquum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nec vincit Ratio hoc, tantund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccet, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Qui te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s caules ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i freg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rti,</l>
               <l>Et qui n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> ſacralegeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>AD SIT</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>REGVLA,</hi> peccatit qua p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>as irr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aquas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>.1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:877:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:877:2"/>
            <head>To the GRAVE and GODLIE VVISE, <hi>in Higheſt Authoritie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> GENTLEMAN a friend and louer of learning,</hi> comming into a free Schoole, wher diuers yong Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers were learning their Grammer, deſirous to feele how they thryud at their Bookes by ſome familiar queſtion; demaunded, (their Huiſhers ſtanding by) <hi>When an Engliſh is giuen to be made into Latine, whats firſt to be done?</hi> The anſwere is eaſie, namely, <hi>To ſeeke out the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Verbe:</hi> yet all ſtoode ſilent, and halfe amazed, till <hi>ONE</hi> at the laſt (the Queſtion eſt-ſoones repeated, and hee vrged to ſay,<note place="margin">Men affecting to doe the Prince and Common-wealth ſeruice, in ſome honeſt calling, enter the charge of Cuſtumes ſimply, &amp; doubting no harme.</note> 
               <hi>What was to bee done</hi>) replied; <hi>NO HARME SIR I HOPE, at leaſt THAT I VVOT OF.</hi> Which the Gentleman taking in very good part, as ſuſpecting rather ignorance in the Huiſhers, then want of wit in the Schollers, departed, ſmyling.</p>
            <p>Moſt <hi>REVEREND</hi> and <hi>RIGHT HONORABLE.</hi> This Queſtion &amp; Anſwere includeth the preſent eſtate of al the ſtudents in the Schoole of her <hi>Maieſties Cuſtumes,</hi> where ſuch as the Teachers be, ſuch are the Schollers. There is a reaſon for al things. And the reaſon hereof is not ſo much, for want of wit or will in the Learners, <hi>To deale iuſtly betweene the Prince and her People</hi> (which in this kind of doctrine is ſuppoſed to be the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal verbe</hi>) as in the ignorant &amp; indiſcrete Husſhers, who whilſt the graue <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Moderators</hi> of the Schoole, were diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and buſied in the ſtudie &amp; practiſe of higher points of learning; haue vſed no method, but bearing the Schollers.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>"Qui paria eſſe volunt peccata, Ipſique laborant</l>
               <l>"Cum ventum ad verum eſt: Senſus moreſque repugnant,</l>
               <l>"Atque <hi>ipſa vtilitas, Iuſti</hi> prope mater &amp; <hi>Aequi.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Which kind of diſcipline, diſcouraging al men &amp; driuing many good wits from the Schoole, to the ſecrete iniury of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; forcde me to my Booke, and as well as I could, to <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſe</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>my leſſon, meaning thereby with the foreſaid plaine Scholler <hi>(NO HARME AT ALL)</hi> ſuch therefore as it is, I haue briefely ſet downe in the <hi>Diſcours</hi> following. The Matter whereof being partly drawne from mine owne Patience and experience, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued and learned from others: The Forme is meerely mine owne, and hath for my warrant the Rules of my Grammer.</p>
            <p>But ſince <hi>Things are then wel done, when things are wel taken;</hi> to cleare and acquite me from partiall clamor, or the ſinne of preſumption, The Will appliant to Reaſon, is guiltleſſe of paſsion, and Nature ouerborne appeales to Neceſsitie. <hi>Quae quod cogit, ipſa, ſolet vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> defendere.</hi> Hard therefore and aboue meaſure extreame ſhould their caſes appeare, that ſtill ſubiect to beating, might neither bemoane themſelues, nor be ſuffred to crie. And ſo much the rather, when as <hi>(SO FAR AS I VVOT OF)</hi> in all their Complaints,<note place="margin">The Lawe of Nature and Nations both, allow all men, to ſtand in defence of their Callings and honeſt Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> there is nothing concluded nor included, at leaſt intended therby, but a natural defence of their honeſt reputation in that kind of Calling, which the Law it ſelfe by great wiſdome hath laid out, and reſerued <hi>For men of the beſt ſorte onely,</hi> and a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Zeale to find out thereby <hi>The principall Verbe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="maxims">
            <pb facs="tcp:877:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Principles</hi> and generall <hi>Maximes,</hi> whereon this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> is grounded: making an <hi>Epitome</hi> of the whole.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll <hi>Common-wealths</hi> are eſtabliſhed and maintained by <hi>Lawes.</hi> The life of <hi>Law,</hi> is <hi>Reaſon. Reaſon</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Lawes</hi> aymes at <hi>Equitie. Equitie</hi> is guided by <hi>Certaintie</hi> and <hi>Indifferencie,</hi> the two Ballances of <hi>Iuſtice;</hi> for where theſe two faile, men runne into <hi>Extremities. Extremities</hi> find out <hi>Shifts. Shifts</hi> incurre <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition. Suſpition</hi> argues <hi>Ignorance. Ignorance</hi> groping for truth lights on <hi>Errors. Errors</hi> proue <hi>Miſchiefes.</hi> priuate <hi>Miſchiefes</hi> turne to publike <hi>Inconueniences;</hi> the high way to <hi>Diſcord, Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion.</hi> And as things grow confounded, <hi>Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> by conſequence encreaſe more and more. Which as pudled waters and corrupted ayre, breede and engender nothing, but creeping <hi>Informers,</hi> noyſome <hi>Caterpillers,</hi> rauenous <hi>Harpyes</hi> and ſuch like vermine, to vexe and torment a <hi>State</hi> withall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By meanes whereof,</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>¶ The PRINCE is abuſed, and ſo iuſtly offended.</item>
               <item>¶ The MARCHANTS are weried and generally grieued.</item>
               <item>¶ The CVSTVMERS ouerburdened are iniuriouſly diſgraced.</item>
               <item>¶ The COMMONS of all ſorts empayring, repine: <hi>And</hi>
               </item>
               <item>¶ The PORT-TOVVNES decay.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The reading of whoſe ſeueral Complaints, may make any VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERSTANDING READER, able to be his owne Iudge, and ſee. How in the preſent diſordered eſtate of Cuſtume ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 TRAFFICKE is become empayred, and ſo conſequently her Maieſties <hi>Cuſtumes</hi> diminiſhed.</item>
               <item>2 The COMMON-WEALTH growes diſordred, and dayly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poucriſhed. <hi>And</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 The STATE (beſides the Common Enemie) is engaged and vnkindly at Iarre, with her ancient <hi>Allyes,</hi> and beſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine <hi>Friends.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:877:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:877:4"/>
            <head>The ſtate of the CVSTVMES. Specially <hi>in the</hi> OVT-PORTES <hi>of</hi> this Realme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>REAT HATH BEENE THE CARE, AND THE Inuentions ſundrie, that haue beene vndertaken, for the aduauncing, collecting and true anſwering, of all ſuch Duties as vpon things by way of Merchandize,<note place="margin">Cuſtumes <hi>defined.</hi>
               </note> Croſsing the Seas, are either vented out or brought into this Land, according to Lawes and Contracts to that end.</p>
            <p>But as in the State of a natural body, thoſe diſeaſes prooue of moſt dangerous conſequence, that are of longeſt breeding, and moſt deſperate to cure, whoſe cauſes are vnknowne: ſo fares it at this day with that, which highly importing the whole Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, is of it ſelfe, no ſmall nor idle portion in the body of the Princes Reuenues. Namely, the ſtate of the CVSTVMES; ſpecially in the OVT-PORTES of this Realme. The preſent condition whereof, being neerely obſerued, may bee fitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to the diſeaſes of the body,<note place="margin">Reſembled to inueterate Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</note> which the Phiſitians terme <hi>Morbs Chronici.</hi> For as they engendred with time, not ſeene to at firſt, or but ſlightly regarded, make worke at the laſt for <hi>Apothecaries</hi> and <hi>Surgeons,</hi> leading the part infected ſtill from ill to worſe: ſo in the occaſions and continuance of theſe kinds of ſores or diſorders, for want of due inſpection or true informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the ſeruice growes confounded; Offences by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence encreaſe more and more.</p>
            <p>For remedy whereof, though confident <hi>Emperiks</hi> neuer ſo boldly, with their violent and repercuſsiue medicines, from all parts obtrude themſelues, ſucking profit thereby at one hand or other: When all is done &amp; ſayd, the Graue and Wiſe Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">Fit for none but graue and Phiſitians of experience</note> muſt put to their hands, who proceeding by method from <hi>An fieri poſsit,</hi> to <hi>Quid fieri debet;</hi> by the pulſe and <hi>Symptoma</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the diſeaſe, and conferring with the Patients themſelues, finding the cauſe; proportion Receipts for remedy.</p>
            <q>
               <l>For if Vrines proue deceitfull, and Patients neuer ſpeake:</l>
               <l>No maruell then, if Phyſicke faile and medicines be to ſeeke.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In which reſpect, for the better information of the State of this Cauſe, this preſent Diſcourſe is conceiued,<note place="margin">The motiue of this Diſcourſe</note> that through it the VNDERSTANDING READER AND WISE IN AVTHORITIE, by reading onely, without paſsion or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie might be their owne Iudges. Wherein (if for the length in ſhew it ſeeme to be tedious) ſo the Forme for the plaineneſſe proue not off enſiue;<note place="margin">The oftner read the better vnderſtood.</note> the Matter for importance deſerues more then a reading.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:5"/>
¶ <hi>Priuatio praeſupponit habitum.</hi> Sicknes doth imply a habit of helth, &amp; the diſproportioned diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any <hi>Function,</hi> doth argue an intention &amp; poſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Order.</hi> To the vnderſtanding wherof, ſince parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities &amp; circumſtances do beſt approoue and lay open the trueth or falſehood of any <hi>Action</hi> or <hi>Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> In the Conſultation and Reſolution of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of CVSTVMES,<note place="margin">The Argument.</note> as well for their due Collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and true Anſwering, as the infallible meanes of their orderly aduancing, to the glorious demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and happie vpholding of the wealth and peace of this State and Kingdome, both at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: <hi>Fower things</hi> doe firſt offer themſelues to mind and neceſſarie conſideration.</p>
            <list>
               <item>¶ 1 The CAVSE or Ground, whence ſuch Duties growe and haue their firſt being.</item>
               <item>¶ 2 The MATTER what, and where vpon ſuch Duties grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are to be paide and taken.</item>
               <item>¶ 3 The PERSONS, whome ſuch Duties either immediatly or by conſequence touch and concerne.</item>
               <item>¶ 4 The FORME how to collect ſuch Duties, fit and peculiar to the CAVSE, MATTER and PERSONS.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt therefore of the</hi> CAVSE <hi>of</hi> CVSTVMES <hi>for Orders ſake, and ſo of the reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THe Nature of all things that conſiſt in <hi>Action,</hi> is beſt ſeene and valued, by the worthines of that <hi>Obiect</hi> and <hi>End</hi> where to it tendeth.</p>
            <p>The higheſt <hi>Obiect</hi> of humaine <hi>Actions</hi> (GOD onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) is the MAIESTIE of our SOVERAIGNE and GOOD of our COVNTRY. And there is no <hi>Action</hi> more dutiful, then at all hands to amplifie the honour of the one, and to procure the peace of the other; nor any more odious, then wittingly or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to impaire the <hi>Meanes,</hi> mutually ment for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of either.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The maine drift and purpoſe of the Argument.</note>It followeth then as a conſequence of all ſides to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on; <hi>That to maintaine the Princes Reuenewes,</hi> and to further the <hi>proſperitie of her people</hi> is, or ought to be, the ſpeciall care of euery mans beſt endeuour.</p>
            <p>But, as in all things that depend on CAVSES, and conſiſt of MATTER and FORME, where the proprieties of either are
<pb facs="tcp:877:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>not rightly vnderſtood nor ſeriouſly obſerued, the firſt <hi>Error</hi> breeding <hi>Miſchiefe,</hi> leades the high way to <hi>Diſorder</hi> and ſo to <hi>Confuſion:</hi> ſo fares it at this day with the State and argument of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> namly the publike duties of CVSTVMES. That as well for the CAVSE whence they proceede and their MATTER what it is, as in their FORME how to ſtop the courſe of <hi>Errors</hi> and currant of <hi>Abuſes,</hi> hath of long time bene and yet is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition diuerſly and ſtrangely debated. Wherein howſoeuer <hi>Confuſion</hi> encreaſe generall offences, <hi>Holding the Actors next hand ſtill ſubiect to ſuſpition and blame.</hi> (<hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> bearing the ſway)<note n="*" place="margin">The ATTORNEY and</note> 
               <hi>Experience</hi> and<note n="⸪" place="margin">SOLICITOR generall: for the <hi>Prince</hi> and her <hi>People.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Truth</hi> arguing the caſe before <hi>Equitie</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> diſpute the Queſtion, and reſolue it thus.</p>
            <p>Al <hi>Effects</hi> work only by &amp; liue or dy with their proper CAVSES.</p>
            <p>All CAVSES are either <hi>Efficient, Materiall, Formall,</hi> or <hi>Finall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cuſtumes deſcribed.</note>¶ CVSTVMES are the Princes publike <hi>Duties,</hi> growing by TRAFFICK, on <hi>Marchandize</hi> outward and inward, payable according to the <hi>Equitie</hi> of poſitiue <hi>Lawes</hi> and forraine <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts,</hi> freely and onely giuen <hi>For defence of the Realme and ſafe paſſage at Seas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus CVSTVMES follow TRAFFICK as the <hi>Effect</hi> doth the CAVSE;<note place="margin">The CAVSE.</note> in which regard the <hi>Merchant</hi> at all hands is to be cheriſhed, fauoured and encouraged in euery common-welth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Trafficke deſcribed.</note>¶ TRAFFICKE is a mutuall bartering, or buying &amp; ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Vendible wares, by Merchants, Subiects or Strangers, at Marketes conuenient, according to the Rulers of Reciproke Commerce, generally entending the honour of the Prince and proſperitie of the Common-weale.</p>
            <p>There appeare in TRAFFICK by this diſcription fower ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall parts, to bee ſeuerally conſidered and iointly maintained, as being ſo eſſentially coherent, and neceſſarily concurrent, that where any one is failing, the reſt haue no longer being. To wit, MATTER (as <hi>Vendible wares.</hi> Secondly PERSONS (Merchants <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,</hi> or <hi>Strangers.</hi> Thirdly, PLACE (at <hi>Markets conuenient</hi>) Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ORDER <hi>(rules of reciproke Commerce.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt in the Condition of the MATTER whatſoeuer it be GOODNES only (more or leſſe) makes it <hi>Vendible,</hi> as reſpected &amp; fit for <hi>Trades.</hi> All GOODNES is either by <hi>Nature</hi> or by <hi>Art:</hi> And as in GOODNES there is a proportion alwaies anſwerable to the firſt MATTER, wherein it conſiſteth: ſo in <hi>Trades,</hi> the bleſsing of God by <hi>Nature,</hi> and the benefit of <hi>Induſtrie</hi> by <hi>Art,</hi> is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly more or leſſe admired, to the ſpeciall reputation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the PERSONS and PLACES that firſt afford them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In the quality of the PERSON of the <hi>Merchant,</hi> whoſoeuer he be, Subiect or Stranger; onely <hi>Loyaltie</hi> and <hi>Alliance,</hi> makes his
<pb facs="tcp:877:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>TRAFFICK auowed, without diſtinction of Sex or yeares: For with knowne Traitors or open enemies, the Lawe admits no Commerce.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In the PLACES <hi>Conueniencie</hi> at home or abroad, <hi>Eaſines</hi> of Acceſſe by Sea or land and publike <hi>Freedome</hi> with <hi>Safetie</hi> for MATTER and PERSONS, is onely regarded in all <hi>Martes</hi> and <hi>Markets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 And the beſt Rules for ORDER to direct TRAFFICK by, are they which being preciſely ſquared out to the <hi>Generalitie, Indifferencie</hi> and <hi>Certaintie</hi> of the Lawes of the land and forrain Contracts, admit no particular, partiall nor doubtfull; deceipt, iniurie nor diſturbance, to MATTER, PERSONS, nor PLACE.</p>
            <p>Thus TRAFFICK ſupported by fower ſpeciall Pillers; The firſt is grounded on GOODNES. All GOODNES is needefull. TRAFFICK therefore either outward or inward of things bred at home or abroad; in reſpect of the <hi>Vſe</hi> thereof ought to bee <hi>Generall.</hi> For looke what the Soule is to the outward <hi>Actions</hi> of the body, in ordering each member: ſo, as to Nature ſeemes fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for the good of the whole Man: Such is the vſe of TRAFICK in diſpoſing <hi>Misteries</hi> and <hi>Trades</hi> to the behoofe of the whole Common-wealth. A conſideration in no part of Ciuill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment to bee neglected, much leſſe in this great CAVSE of CVSTVMES. For as much as the GOOD intended thereby both to MATTER, PERSONS, and PLACES, by the rules of <hi>Equitie</hi> is ſo due to <hi>All,</hi> as cannot bee iuſtly reſtrained or denied vnto <hi>Any,</hi> without diſorder and confuſion. <hi>Bonum autem quo communius, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o melius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From TRAFFICKE therefore CVSTVMES deryue their firſt <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and being, and by it encreaſe; to the <hi>Honor</hi> of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and proſperitie of <hi>Common-wealthes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude; TRAFFICK is the true and aſſured practiſe of that miſticall Phyloſophie (wherein ſo many wits haue ſpent themſelues, and blowne the coales in vaine) whoſe heauenly <hi>Elixar</hi> (GOODNES) the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lapis Philoſophicus.</note> by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſublimation, applyed to <hi>Materials,</hi> begets <hi>Miſteries</hi> in <hi>Trades,</hi> and purging all droſſe of deceipt from <hi>Trades,</hi> turnes <hi>Trades</hi> into <hi>Mettals,</hi> and all <hi>Mettals</hi> into pure <hi>Siluer</hi> and fine <hi>Gold:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vniuerſalis Medecina.</note> And that generall <hi>Reſtoratiue,</hi> which eaſing all griefe in <hi>Sores,</hi> ſuppling all <hi>Sores</hi> in <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and curing all <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> in particular Members, holdes the whole Body of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale</hi> in perfect health. The ſacred Rules whereof, as no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <hi>Couetiſe</hi> could euer comprehend, nor confident <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks</hi> attaine to practiſe, ſo none of priuate <hi>Diſcretion</hi> or <hi>Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> may preſume to alter or control; as being a Doctrine and Study, peculiar to the GRAVE and GODLY WISE onely in higheſt Authoritie, and for PRINCES themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The MATTER or Subiect,<note place="margin">2 MATTER.</note> is al kind of wares that by way of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe</hi> croſsing the ſeas are either tranſported and vented out, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported or broght into the Realme; whereupon ſuch paiments are col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, as <hi>(For defence of the Realme, and ſafe paſſage at Seas)</hi> loyally offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and graciouſly accepted, the Lawes of TRAFFICK doe recorde by the names and titles. Of
<list>
                  <item>CVSTVMS
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Great and</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Small.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>and</item>
                  <item>SVBSIDIES of
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Pondage, and</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tonnage.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The word CVSTVMES albeit it be vſed as a general name for al Duties vpon goods croſsing the Seas, both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: yet it hath his peculiar and diſtinct ſignification. And is either that Dutie which is taken vpon Woolles, Woolfels, Tinne, Lead, and other Staple wares of this land, by the name of <hi>Grand</hi> CVSTVME; Or the Dutie of three pence vppon the pound &amp;c. Yeelded onely by Strangers, by the title of PETIT-CVSTVME.</p>
            <p>SVBSIDY, is but the <hi>Genus</hi> or <hi>Generall</hi> title to other duties, namely, <hi>Pondage</hi> and <hi>Tonnage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pondage</hi> is a SVBSIDY paide generally vpon all <hi>Marchandize,</hi> croſsing the Seas, of twelue pence the pound (not otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by ſpeciall Statute as is that of Corne). Whereof it ſortes the name of <hi>Pondage,</hi> though in reſpect of the vſe, it be more vſually called SVBSIDY, <hi>Quia datur in ſubſidium Principi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tonnage,</hi> is alſo a SVBSIDY diuerſly collected according to diuers Statutes limiting the ſame; being either generally gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for defence of the Realme, and free trafique on the Seas, as the <hi>Tonnage</hi> of Wines, or for the particular reliefe of ſome Port or Towne, as that of Douer.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:7"/>
               <head>¶ The MATTER being thus laide open: The PERSONS, are next to bee weighed;<note place="margin">3. The PERSONS</note> whome theſe Duties do for ſeuerall reſpectes concerne, Either</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Immediately</hi> or directly, as
<list>
                     <item>The PRINCE to whom they are giuen and by Law due.</item>
                     <item>The MARCHANT, that by Lawe is to pay them.</item>
                     <item>The OFFICER, ſpecially appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Collect them to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mediately,</hi> or by conſequence; in regarde of free <hi>Trafficke.</hi> Viz.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Generally,</hi> The whole COMMONS of this Realme.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Specially</hi> the PORTE-TOWNES whoſe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, are
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Artificers and Trades. or</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>M. <hi>of Shippes and Mariners.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The .4. <note place="margin">4. FORME.</note> thing to be neceſſarily thought vpon and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, is the FORME and maner of collection, fit &amp; anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the MATTER and PERSONS. <hi>Forma dat eſſe rei.</hi> For without it, the <hi>Prince,</hi> though much be giuen, is voide of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie meanes to be iuſtly anſwered, and ſo not ſatisfied. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, the <hi>Marchant</hi> though much be due, knowes not how and with what diſcharge to pay it. And without it the <hi>Officer,</hi> though much be to be receiued, is without ſufficient warrant to collect it by.</p>
            <p>In the direction whereof therefore, <hi>Common equitie</hi> is to be reſpected. <hi>viz.</hi> That is in al other Duties hauing one and the ſame ground <hi>(Like twins)</hi> as namely thoſe vpon lands &amp; goods <hi>(De paribus autem est idem iudicium)</hi> the Aſſeſſe once agreed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by competent authoritie; doth intitle and ſatisfie the <hi>Prince,</hi> binde and acquite the <hi>Subiect,</hi> direct and warrant the <hi>Collector,</hi> and ſo fulfils the Lawe by giuing euery one his right; ſo in theſe duties vpon <hi>Merchandiſe</hi> both inward and outward, the Aſſeſſe or Rate of things once digeſted, is or ought to be a rule generall and inuiolable; the <hi>Equitie</hi> whereof, conſiſting in the <hi>Certentie</hi> and <hi>Indifferencie</hi> of Aſſeſſement, according to a
<pb facs="tcp:877:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>reaſonable valuation of things in vſe, and ſo experſſely ſet downe and named, and commaunding the like in Matters occurring.</p>
            <p>But by reaſon of ſome vneuen cariage in the MATTER and preſent FORME; the PERSONS aforeſaid in their ſeuerall degrees and places, haue their <hi>Offences, Griefes,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints.</hi> The knowledge whereof comprehendes the whole State of the Cauſe in queſtion, and giueth light to the grounds and occaſions of the preſent diſorders. <hi>For</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The PRINCE offended.</note>¶ Firſt, the PRINCE, is two waies highly diſpleaſed; namely, either in that her Duties are by the <hi>Merchants</hi> defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or by the Collectors ill aunſwered into the Exchequer: or in that they ſeeme not ſo well husbanded for her, as priuate Perſons by Leaſes doe make them for themſelues. The ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of whome, may make a way to relieue others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The MERCHANT grieued.</note>¶ The MERCHANTS griefes are likewiſe double, <hi>Publike</hi> and <hi>Priuate.</hi> For <hi>Generally</hi> they bemoane themſelues, that as <hi>Subiects</hi> deſirous to liue vnder the rule and direction of the Law; they are driuen to incurre the danger thereof, for want of <hi>Indifferent</hi> and <hi>Certaine</hi> proceedings. For where as one and the ſame Law (though by ſeuerall Statutes) doe binde them to anſwere the <hi>Prince</hi> Subſidies, and other duties on their lands and their goods, as well as their Merchandize; yet in paying the one (though held with more aſſurance at home, and that paide happily but once in the yeare) the Aſſeſſe is ſet downe with a conſideration of each mans eſtate and charge; and in Collecting the other (though the payments be more frequent and dayly for one thing or other) there is farre leſſe regard or feeling of the hazards they runne, by Sea, by Enemies, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie winds, Banckrowts and ill Markets. And whereas in the payments on lands and goods, the Collector alone being ſatisfied, the partie is acquit, without further charge, trouble or delay: in the matter of <hi>Merchandiſe,</hi> beſide the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors</hi> due, <hi>Impoſitions</hi> and a multiplicitie of irregular exactions and fees to <hi>Searchers, Comptrollers, Surueyours, Waiters, Wayers, Packers, Scauagers,</hi> their <hi>Deputies, Clerkes, Seruants</hi> (and ſuch like) is ſuch a ſecrete burden, that in 6 or 7 yeares, the payments in this kind, doe counteruaile their Stockes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
¶ <hi>Priuatly</hi> they grieue, that amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues Trades vnder <hi>Companies</hi> and <hi>Societies</hi> are drawne and abridged into a few mens hands; wherein, beſides the wrong offered to the Law and general freedome of the land, euen within themſelues alſo, the welthier and beſt grounded, by oddes of ſtockes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints and other aduantages, driue the weaker to the walles. That one <hi>Porte</hi> ſeemes to giue Law to all the reſt, without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Law, reaſon or Pollicie; the daunger whereof, moe ſee and lament, then know how to preuent or remedie. That in all <hi>Ports</hi> extremities attend them driuing them to this iſſue, either to quit their Trades altogether,<note place="margin">Extremities driue the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants to ſhifts.</note> or to worke it out by fauour at one <hi>Porte</hi> or other, to the diſpleſure of the <hi>Prince,</hi> as if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceald he Cuſtumes, when they get leaſt by it, as may bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the falling of ſundrie, and decay of a great many.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The OFFICER com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth.</note>¶ The OFFICER, thirdly, hath his griefes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints; for vnfoulding whereof, many things concurring are firſt to be laide open, namely, who that OFFICER is, and what he is; for the ſeruice is pretended and attended on by many, each valuing himſelfe aboue other, and his place and ſtanding to be of moſt importance. In the viewing of whome a part and a ſunder, REASON ſhall the better diſcerne and iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them.<note place="margin">Ariſt. coutra Sophiſt.</note> For <hi>Quaedam ſunt &amp; non videntur; Quaedam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur &amp; non ſunt omnino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Cuſtumes</hi> being <hi>Effects</hi> of that CAVSE, whoſe Actions are conuerſant about no meaner <hi>Obiects</hi> then the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of our Soueraigne, and proſperitie of her People; imply a Seruice, which as it requires men of ſpeciall regard and truſt: ſo none may vndertake it, but with authoritie and power giuen them in lawfull maner. In the Function therefore of an <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer</hi> of CVSTVMES.<note place="margin">Fower grounds to diſcerne by, betweene the neceſſarie inſtitution and needeleſſe or bootles vſe of their Functions</note> 4. things are to be wayed and conſidered, to iuſtifie the lawfulneſſe and neceſsitie of his calling. 1. The Inſtitution, that giues him power to medle with Duties of that nature. 2. The PORT and Places allotted him for the exerciſe of his <hi>Office.</hi> 3. The diligent performance of his ſeruice, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the importance &amp; exigence of his charge. 4. And laſtly the Countenance and proportionable Maintenaunce which in that reſpect he deſerues and receiues.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Officers</hi> therefore in the OVT-PORTES are fowre in number, and knowne by the names of CVSTOMER, SEARCHER, COMPTROLLER and SVPERVISORS.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:8"/>
               <note place="margin">The CVSTVMERS <hi>Office</hi>
               </note>The CVSTVMERS hold their places by the Princes let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents &amp; great ſeale of England, wherby they are authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and warranted, appointed &amp; named <hi>Collectors,</hi> as well of all ancient duties vpon Wool, Woolfels &amp;c. termed <hi>Grand Cuſtume</hi> and of the <hi>Petie Cuſtume,</hi> paid onely by Strangers: as alſo of the Subſidie of <hi>Pondage</hi> and <hi>Tonnage,</hi> graunted her Maieſtie in <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> 
               <q>of her Raigne, during her life <hi>Pro defenſione Regni, &amp; cuſtodia Maris.</hi> Concluding all with this Cloſe. <hi>Ita quod de denarijs inde prouenientibus ad Scaccarit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m noſtrum nobis reſpondeas.</hi>
               </q> In which behalfe for the Princes ſecuritie, before the deliuerie or receipt of any letters Patents, the Cuſtumers are bound by themſelues and good ſuerties, and ſworn beſides at their admiſsions, to do their endeuors, <hi>To deale iuſtly betwéene the Prince and her People</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The whole ſeruice towardes the Prince and people, lyable to the Cuſtumers onely.</note>The PRINCE being ſecured, next followes the ſeruice of the <hi>Merchant.</hi> On whoſe behalfe, if any deniall or vnlawfull delay be vſed to his hurt or hinderance, the Lawe calles the <hi>Cuſtumer</hi> in queſtion onely, and in that reſpect, the <hi>Office</hi> ſeale is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, and the forme of all <hi>Warrants,</hi> of <hi>Cockets</hi> and <hi>Bonds,</hi> to the vſe of the <hi>Queene</hi> runne onely in his name, as wel from PORT to PORT as otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>This being the effect and whole ſumme of the Seruice; is the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> office and charge onely,<note place="margin">12. Ric. 2. cap. 2. And ſuch had they neede to be, for no <hi>Officer</hi> in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth may doe more good or harme, then a Cuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in a ſhire, or the Townes of his charge.</note> whome therefore the <q>Law doth point out and choſe, <hi>From amongſt the beſt and moſt ſufficient men to be found, to the Lord Treaſurers eſtimation.</hi>
               </q> And is no more indeede then may well be performed by ſuch a one; Prouided the Law be his Load-ſtone, &amp; Equitie his Compaſſe, and enabled withall with <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>Maintenance,</hi> fit for his calling.</p>
            <p>Thus the whole ſeruice, as appeares, hath but two ends, the ſatisfaction of the <hi>Prince,</hi> &amp; diſpatch of the <hi>Merchant.</hi> To which end, for the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> reliefe, that being buſied within doores, might want helpe abroad, out of the neceſsitie of the ſeruice: The SEARCHER was created:<note place="margin">The SEARCHERS <hi>Office deſcribed.</hi>
               </note> Whoſe Office is to ſee that no water paſſe by, without the Grinders knowledge, but either to ſend them to the CVSTVME houſe, or driue them to the Exchequer, as the words of his Patent doe import and commaund: ſo as taking the moyetie of al forfaits and ſeiſures <q>for his paines, <hi>De altera medietate nobis reſpondeas, &amp; fidelem inde computum in Scaccario noſtro reddas.</hi> And thus what the <hi>Cuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> may not conueniently doe, the <hi>Searcher</hi> performes.</q> Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping entries of all <hi>Cockets, Bonds &amp;c.</hi> paſsing by him from the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> hands, as of his owne ſeiſures, and accomptable yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the truth of his doings.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
But as all Officers of accompt are ſubiect to ſuſpition, and the man once ſuſpected, is ſaid to be halfe hanged: So with <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumers</hi> aboue all men (as things are miſtaken) it is not enough to be an honeſt man. For the faults or weakneſſe of any one, is made a conſequence to call the reſt in queſtion, as if all were caſt in one mould; without diſtinguiſhing the true Cauſes, whereby one Error is made the Author of an other. Hence grew the inſtitution of a third <hi>Officer</hi> in name for an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſeruice; for wanting matter to make a new function: He is to ſet with the <hi>Cuſtumer;</hi> and in al things to imitate his doings, <hi>Et quaſi actum agere.</hi> This man albeit as the <hi>Cuſtumer</hi> is either honeſt or diſhoneſt, be needleſſe or booteleſſe (only the <hi>Prince</hi> may charge her ſelfe with fees to as many new Officers as ſhee pleaſe) what wants in eſſence of a function,<note place="margin">Before her Maieſties time all Cuſtumers acomptes, were written in Rolles. The COMPTROLLER.</note> is recompenced in title: and for keeping a <hi>Counter-rowle</hi> of the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> doings, is in his Patent called a <hi>Comptroller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Though Rules and directions wherewith <hi>Functions</hi> are bounded, propound indeede and intend perfection. Yet not that, whereto none can attaine: but ſuch as all men muſt and may ayme at, to the end, that as farre as humaine care and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight can extend; it may take place. In which reſpect, what more effectuall Bond of dutifull endeuour may be vrged, then the vowes and pledges which <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> giue for their fidelities at their firſt admiſsion? The nature of their ſeruice holding them withal, ſo ſubiect to care and feare.</p>
            <p>In whoſe behalfe therefore and ſpeciall defence: 1. Here might be much ſpoken to approue and maintaine, that in all Offices of charge and neceſſarie truſt,<note place="margin">Two generall Propoſitions, affirmatiue, and neceſsarie.</note> hee that for his fidelitie giues the vttermoſt of all ſecuritie in vſe amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ought to be abſolutely credited. And that, that being done; all cautions beſides, are but booteleſſe effects of <hi>Ielouſie</hi> and <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition,</hi> iniurious to the Reputation of that <hi>Officer</hi> and hurtfull to the ſeruice. 2. And that where the pledge is once giuen and taken, which is the vttermoſt of all ſecurities in vſe amongſt Chriſtians: Of conſequence if that <hi>Officer</hi> bee diſhoneſt, he is ill choſen, and ſo fit to be remooued; or the Function in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or forme defectiue, and ſo fit to be reformed.</p>
            <p>But truth is called the daughter of <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Practize</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> the Midwiues that bring her to light, for the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this third <hi>Prouiſion</hi> or <hi>Caution,</hi> in time gaue eaſie way to a fourth kind of <hi>Officer,</hi> and ſo may doe to the fift and a ſixt <hi>in infinitum,</hi> ſo long as the grounds and cauſes of offences are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken or vnknowne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:9"/>
¶ <hi>Ignorance</hi> is called the mother of <hi>Error.</hi> Of <hi>Errors</hi> come <hi>Miſchiefes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Truth beſt found out by knowledge of Error.</note> and <hi>priuate Miſchiefes</hi> proue <hi>publike Inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences:</hi> which breeding <hi>Confuſion,</hi> point out <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Perfection</hi> as <hi>Cauſes</hi> grow known. So that, <hi>Faelix qui poterit rerum cognoſcere Cauſas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CVSTVMES paid by <hi>Merchants</hi> are ſubiect to TRAFFICK as the Effect to the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Trafficke ſubiect to Occaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions and Times.</note>TRAFFICK ryſeth and falleth with occaſions and <hi>Times,</hi> the obſeruing whereof, requireth <hi>Experience</hi> and <hi>Iudgement</hi> to direct; and <hi>Freedome</hi> with <hi>Juduſtrie</hi> to manage the ſame. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples wherof are all Owners of lands, that by diſtinguiſhing Soyles, and obſeruing of Seaſons, make vſe of their grounds.</p>
            <p>But, as if a Lord of a Mannour, that intending to make the beſt of his own, by his immediate Seruants, though the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds be excellent, fertile, and good, giues charge notwithſtanding, and expreſly forbids them both the vſe of the Plough,<note place="margin">Cuſtumers forbidden all Trades and Trafficke.</note> and all means beſids of manuring their ſoiles: wherby their wils wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting freedome to approue their endeuours, they reape none other yeelde, then as nature affordes; and ſo at the ende of harueſt, falling out with his Seruants, farmes the Land vnto Strangers, who neereſt themſelues, firſt ſerue their own turnes,<note place="margin">The farming of Cuſtumes vnnaturall, and not ſo good to the Prince, as iniurious to the Subiect.</note> and in rayſing their rents (for the moſt part) make ſpoyle of the grounds: So fares it with the Seruants and lands of this great Feeld of reuenues. And no meruaile at al, for where things are paſt ouer without diſtinction of <hi>Times, Perſons</hi> and <hi>Place;</hi> the <hi>Error</hi> in iudgement makes the <hi>Actor</hi> next hand ſuſpected and blamde.</p>
            <p>Thus firſt grew the occaſion, that the CVSTVME of ſundrie things became farmed out to ſundrie Perſons, for yearely rents certaine, and ſet termes of yeares. But with what vncertaine ſucceſſe, the times haue declared, and the perſons haue found.</p>
            <p>For witneſſe whereof, omitting times paſt to begin neerer hand; about the xij. of the <hi>Queene,</hi> M. <hi>Smith</hi> tooke the <hi>Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umes</hi> of ſome PORTS to farme,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Smith.</hi>
               </note> whoſe induſtrie made his gaines ſo enuied, that all was reſumde at the end of his yeares.</p>
            <p>After him, Sir <hi>Frauncis Walſingham</hi> was wonne to the like for ſome PORTS elſe where;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Fra. Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham.</note> but miſsing the methode, how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he thriued, after his death, the remainder of his terme was by compoſition ſurrendred vp into her Maieſties hands.</p>
            <p>Then grew it a queſtion (things ſo meeting together) how the ſame might be beſt husbanded, to her Maieſties owne and immediate vſe, that had beene ſo good to ſome others at a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hand. And becauſe the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> at al hands were holden for <hi>Publicans</hi> &amp; <hi>Sinners,</hi> a new &amp; fourth ſort of <hi>Officers</hi> became
<pb facs="tcp:877:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>created, who at the coſt of Sir <hi>Francis</hi> hauing wonne their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience before, vndertooke by themſelues and Deputies, <hi>To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all abuſes,</hi> and <hi>aduance the Queenes Cuſtumes,</hi> in al PORTS of this Realme, LONDON excepted.</p>
            <p>To theſe therfore, being fower in number: a Commiſsion is graunted ioyntly,<note place="margin">4. SVPERVISORS.</note> by the name of SVPERVISORS.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. <hi>Occultatio.</hi> truly deſcribing the ſtate of the ſeruice. Drawen from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in Muſique and Order in building.</note> 
               <hi>To reforme all abuſes,</hi> and <hi>aduance the Queenes Cuſtumes?</hi> Bid ſuch men wel-come, bee they neuer ſo many; for thats the <hi>Dyapaſon</hi> of all our Muſicke, ſo the more the merier. And the baſe of that building ſo many haue vndertaken, and ſo fewe haue ſet forward; therefore the more hands the lighter worke. Prouided alwaies, they ſing with the Companie, and worke in Gods name. <hi>Hoc opus, hic labor est,</hi> committed to none but <hi>"Men of the best ſort only.</hi> Religious and honeſt indeede, as theſe pretend to be. Yet ſince in this &amp; in al things, <hi>Virtutis laus actio,</hi> and Carpenters are alwaies beſt knowne by their chippes; firſt heare their voices and examine their cunning, for ſo their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and harmonie will ſhewe their skill in Muſicke, and their Diſpoſition and Order in rayſing their worke, will commend their building. For if into a Conſort, ordained to ſing or ſound, <hi>Any</hi> or <hi>Many,</hi> ſhould obtrude themſelues, and taking vp Inſtruments, pretending to tune them, regard neither <hi>Reſts,</hi> nor giue eare to any <hi>Time,</hi> nor ſound the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to find out what compaſſe of <hi>Muſique</hi> they are ableſt to maintaine; but ſing to themſelues, and ſtand winding vp <hi>Strings</hi> till all breake in ſunder; would yee not catch the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> from the hands of ſuch <hi>Tuners,</hi> and as <hi>Perſonnes</hi> either ignorant or impudent, deſire ſuch <hi>Muſitians</hi> of leſſe acquaintance?</p>
            <p>Likewiſe in the framing and rearing ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly peece of building, ſuch as might be the Steeple for <hi>Paules</hi> (a worke faire and farre ſeene, and faiſible enough, for fit and skilfull worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) if <hi>Any</hi> or <hi>Many</hi> vndertaking to aduance it, ſhould begin at the height, and ſo build downeward, or pitching the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thercocke beneath, ſtriue to raiſe the baſe end vpward, would any well aduiſed, ſtand neere ſuch builders for feare of danger? or at leaſt, <hi>Spectatum admiſsi, riſum teneatis Amici?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euen ſuch and no better proues the skill and proceedings of theſe forward <hi>Reformers of abuſes,</hi> and <hi>aduancers of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes.</hi> For whilſt the <hi>Custumers,</hi> ſet vp as it were, and oppoſed with the<note n="a" place="margin">Extremitie.</note> 
               <hi>Diſcant</hi> of their leſſon enioynd them to learne, and finding their<note n="*" place="margin">Marchants.</note> 
               <hi>Inſtruments</hi> not able to maintaine ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe in Muſike; were applying themſelues to the<note n="b" place="margin">The equitie of the Law.</note> 
               <hi>Plaine-ſong,</hi> prickt out to the pleſingeſt <hi>Ditty</hi> that euer was endited, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thus.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Eſt Modus in rebus, ſunt certi denique Fines.</note>There is a Mids betwene Extreames, much like a mark or white</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Quos vltra citraque, nequit conſiſtere Rectum.</note>Whereat who leuels ſhort or gon, can neuer ſhoote aright.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which fitting all<note n="a" place="margin">Raates.</note> 
               <hi>Strings</hi> (the <hi>Searchers</hi> withall, at euery Cloſe ſinging,</p>
            <q>Then Meaſure is the mery Meane for Prince and People.)</q>
            <p>Makes a ſong in it ſelfe of <hi>Good rime</hi> and <hi>Good reaſon,</hi> being perfectly learned and ſung with good <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Tunable voyces;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>daeum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> niſi Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſonans.</note> farre fuller of daintie ſtreines of <hi>Muſique</hi> and heauenly harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, then <hi>Dowlands delight,</hi> or <hi>Perſons</hi> Sweete <hi>In Nomine:</hi> whilſt the <hi>Custumers</hi> (as ſaid is) were thus tuning and ſinging, as their skils and voices would ſerue; <hi>Theſe</hi> ſtep in at aduenture, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace all the<note n="b" place="margin">Cuſtumers.</note> 
               <hi>Muſitians,</hi> for the hoarcenes of ſome, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the<note n="c" place="margin">Marchants.</note> 
               <hi>Instruments</hi> for their low ſound; wind vp the <hi>Strings,</hi> to pitch all at the higheſt, and with a <hi>Catch</hi> of fower parts, like Harpers beſides themſelues, ſing blindly together, Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>No fiſhing to the Sea,</l>
               <l>Nor ſeruice to the King.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which fitting no<note n="a" place="margin">Raates.</note> 
               <hi>Strings</hi> (their <hi>Deputies</hi> at all times lowly repeating,</p>
            <q>
               <l>For all on priuate profit wayt;</l>
               <l>Where things goe guided by Conceit.)</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They that haue eares to heare let them harken, how this priuate and chaunting Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, fitting neither Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments nor voices, proue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to the State, by diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the harmonie and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord betweene the Prince and her People.</note>Makes ſuch a noyſe of No <hi>rime,</hi> or <hi>No reaſon,</hi> ſo full of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, and farre from proportion,<note place="margin">Phrygium me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, omniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> claſsicum &amp; tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ultuoſum.</note> ſo harſh for the voices, and ſtrange for the ſound: that their beſt RECTOR CHORI by no rules of Art can beate out their <hi>Time,</hi> nor temper their <hi>Tune.</hi> Yet ſee their good lucke. They notwithſtanding, thus pleaſing themſelues (whilſt all men beſides, amazd at their Muſicke, and doubtfull ſucceſſe of their building and worke) ſtumbling on <hi>Fortune,</hi> prou'd more happie than wiſe. For indeede and in truth (let REASON <hi>be iudge</hi>) if euer men thriude vnder <hi>Prince</hi> by ignorance and ſeruice in conceite: <hi>Theſe</hi> may well ſay to themſelues, <hi>Plus quandoque valet in rebus promouendis opin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, quam rei veritas.</hi> And <hi>Aſſay ben balla a chi fortuna ſuona.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But bee it knowne to all men by theſe preſents beſides (of <hi>Vnderstanding and iudgement</hi>) that as <hi>omne quod efficit Tale, oportet eſſe magis Tale;</hi> ſo the Law ſetting down the Rates of Cuſtumes, and Authoritie digeſting the <hi>Forme</hi> of their payments, cannot
<pb facs="tcp:877:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>properly be ſaid to increaſe or diminiſh, but by the ſame Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authoritie, or by<note n="a" place="margin">This found Ma. Cuſtumer Smith full true to his happy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, trading in ſome things himſelfe, lending ſtockes vnto others, and dealing friendly with all men, to holde them in doings; which brought in his profit ſtill, for one thing or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> 
               <hi>Trafficks</hi> and <hi>free Commerce</hi> more or leſſe. Otherwiſe, <hi>Noſtrum, magis Noſtrum furi nequit.</hi> Which ſtanding moſt true, and then this noted withall, namely: That as it did not appeare (almoſt in fortie yeares together) how Trades of this thing and that thing by occaſions fell in, and with time increaſed, and ſo of <hi>Cuſtumes</hi> by conſequence, the profits not ſeene nor obſerued, whilſt by Leaſes they ranne through priuate mens hands: ſo it was their better happe than foreſight or skill, to come in at ſuch an inſtant of <hi>Time,</hi> as when both the grace of God in an admirable ſort, gaue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to our<note n="b" place="margin">The plenty of Come at their beginning, their onely good lucke, whereof they called all gaines, Cuſtume, to make a ſhew of ſeruice.</note> graine, and al acceſſes of profit met in one, to her Maieſties immediate vſe together.</p>
            <p>Wherein their <hi>Induſtrie</hi> can claime, neither art nor part, but in Conceite onely. For a full triall whereof (which here to ſet downe, would bee too tedious to reade) a bare collation of<note n="c" place="margin">The want of theſe obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from time to time, holds all Cuſtumers ſo ſubiect, as they are to diſgraces, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious ſuggeſtions.</note> 
               <hi>Matters</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> before them and ſince, for fortie yeares paſt; would ſatisfie all and make this no queſtion.</p>
            <p>(But by way of <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> if to profit the <hi>Hundred</hi> by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing the <hi>Shire</hi> be holden for gaine,<note place="margin">Pretence of zeale to the Prince, without regard of her people, is prepoſterous and dangerous in all publike ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note> then do them no wrong, and let it be graunted which they ſo deſire. Yet take this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, That their ſeruice beginning with <hi>Ecclipſing</hi> the<note n="a" place="margin">The equitie of the Lawe ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed by licences for Corne, ſhewed their ſeruice at the firſt.</note> 
               <hi>Moone,</hi> which neuer fals out but when ſhee is at full: was a naturall conſequence of their immediate <hi>Declining;</hi> and of a fearefull aſſurance of a <hi>Miſchiefe to come.</hi> Wherof one<note n="b" place="margin">The Dearth ſucceeding for want of the foreſtore, exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by priuate licences, againſt the wiſe prouiſion of the Law</note> 
               <hi>Storme</hi> is paſt, God ſend vs no more, and let this bee a leſſon for euer hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that, <hi>To out runne the Law, is to haſt to confuſion.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Yet ſince euery new <hi>Officer,</hi> implyeth new matter fit for a new function, and none may aſſume more to themſelues; then a greater Power doth conferre, (<hi>Theſe</hi> hauing erected to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a place for a priuate <hi>Office,</hi> and deuiſed a publike Seale) as of the <hi>Rest,</hi> ſo ſee their Commiſsion.</p>
            <p>Their Commiſsion is ioyntly, and containes onely their <hi>Name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their <hi>Commiſsion.</hi>
               </note> with a power by themſelues and Deputies; to doe ſuch and ſuch ſeruice, as in a <hi>Schedule</hi> is ordered, and there to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Schedule</hi> hath Articles twelue or thirteene. All formall and nothing materiall at all.<note place="margin">Their <hi>Schedule.</hi>
               </note> For what was aſsigned to <hi>Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollers</hi> before (if that were to purpoſe) is here but repeated; as ſitting &amp; ſigning Cokets and Bonds, and keeping a Booke as the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> doe. With ſearching of Shippes for prohibited wares, contained in the <hi>Searchers</hi> Patent likwiſe. Which ſerues to no vſe; but to charge the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> at each accompts ending, with tedious delayes,<note place="margin">All Miſchiefes are heaped on the Cuſtumers onely.</note> and treble expences for the Auditors paines. Two things onely are ſpecially forbidden, that they
<pb facs="tcp:877:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>delay not the Merchant, nor take any fees, and howe they are performed God knowes beſt, but the Merchant can tell.</p>
            <p>Thus. The CAVSE at the firſt, miſtaken or vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, bred <hi>Error</hi> in the MATTER and FORME, and ſo conſequently <hi>Defects</hi> in the general <hi>Seruice.</hi> Whereof <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> taking hold, accuſed the CVSTVMER as <hi>Actor</hi> next hand and onely bound for all. <hi>Neceſsitie,</hi> for the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> reliefe, fitly found out the vſe of a SEARCHER; but his looſeneſſe and libertie bewraying his <hi>Negligence, (Ne quid aſperius)</hi> made <hi>Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie</hi> and <hi>Suſpition,</hi> deuiſe a kind of COMPTROLLER. His needleſſe or booteleſſe calling; gaue eaſie way to the newe SV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PERVISORS and their <hi>Retinue,</hi> whoſe confident <hi>Preſumption,</hi> combining with <hi>Ignorance</hi> (their ſpecial Vpholders) made them vndertake they knew not what, and to goe forward they carde not how, in <hi>Opinion</hi> onely and <hi>Conceite,</hi> to cure all ſentes of Leekes or Onyons by eating Garlike. Hence grow <hi>Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Diſorders, Offences</hi> and <hi>Complaints</hi> of the PERSONS.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Clodius accuſat Moechum, Catelina Cethegum.</l>
               <l>Quis tulerit Gracchos de ſeditione querentes?</l>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Miſchiefes</hi> whereof, though the MARCHANTS and CVSTVMERS in ſpeciall deuide betweene them; the generall <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences</hi> extend to the PRINCE her ſelfe, her <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes</hi> and moſt <hi>Loyal Subiects;</hi> the importance wherof, the GRAVE and godly WISE; will in due time bee pleaſed to conſider, and remember with all:</p>
            <q>
               <l>That none proue Saints for ſeeming ſo to others,</l>
               <l>Since all are men and all haue ſuckt their Mothers.</l>
            </q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Thus farre the</hi> ATTVRNEY <hi>and</hi> SOLLICITER <hi>generall,</hi> (Experience <hi>and</hi> Truth) <hi>hauing pleaded before</hi> EQVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE <hi>and</hi> REASON, <hi>on the behalfe of</hi> TRAFFICKE, <hi>no leſſe dangerouſly ſupplanted by the</hi> Cuſtumers <hi>diſgrace, then the</hi> Merchants <hi>extremitie; in true Zeale of the</hi> Princes <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Good of her</hi> People; <hi>began here ſeriouſly to lament and bewaile the vnfaithfulnes of ſuch, as ignorantly haue beene the cauſe, or wilfully perſiſt to maintaine the burdening of the</hi> Cuſtume houſes, <hi>with ſuch ſwarmes of vnfit and needleſſe</hi> Inſtruments, <hi>that as Razours cutting off the life of</hi> Cuſtumes, <hi>and wrangling out diſorder by a greater confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo liue by their places, that in time they muſt needes bee the
<pb facs="tcp:877:12"/>death of the</hi> Nurſe <hi>her ſelfe that feedes them. But the wiſdome of the Iudges, moued rather with the weight of the</hi> CAVSE, <hi>then paſsion in their Plea (looking backe to the time) bid them goe forward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Now then, ſee what hath beene ſaid; and ſo haſt to an end.</p>
            <p>The PRINCE (as aforeſaid) is iuſtly offended, &amp; the <hi>Merchant</hi> likewiſe hath laid downe his griefes. Theſe are the fower ſorts of perſons that attend <hi>Custume cauſes,</hi> amongſt whome, if any complaine; theſe laſt haue no reaſon to looke to bee pittied, for that obtruding themſelues into other mens workes, vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a taske exceeding their skill; like men in amaze, ſtriue ſtill to goe forward, and in doing leſſe then nothing, would ſeeme to doe all.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Accuſing the Cuſtumers.</hi> Calumus and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> audacter, vt alis quid adhareat.</note> Not vnlike to inſolent and ignorant Huiſhers, that lawleſſe themſelues, know no rules of teaching, but beating the Schollers.</p>
            <p>But this by the way wilbe wel worth the noting, how gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally iuſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ¶ regula veritatis</note> as neceſſarie true, the old rules of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Propoſitions</hi> of reaſon, continue and ſtand. Namely, <hi>Quam frustra fit per plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, quod fieri potest per pauciores.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ¶ regula Juſtitie</note> And <hi>Inſtitutio ab i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stio inutilis, expostfacto non conualeſcit.</hi> For as theſe <hi>Superuiſors</hi> doubting at the firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ¶ regula ſapientie</note> the holding out of their Deputies good abearing, and wiſely looking into the weake foundation of the <hi>Comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollers,</hi> whoſe Office themſelues foreſaw to be idle, and ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be out-faced; by their new Companie and acceſſe, the ſeruice is become ſo violent, ſo intricate and out of order, that in the confuſion, the <hi>Searchers</hi> that only haue beſt meanes, and by Office ſhould concurre and aſsiſt the <hi>Custumers,</hi> leaue the QVEENE to the <hi>Custume houſe,</hi> and enquire the next way to their owne priuate profit.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cuſtumers onely haue cauſe to complaine.</note>In which diſtreſſe, the CVSTVMERS in diſpleaſure with the <hi>Prince,</hi> in diſgrace with the world, forſaken of their beſt Helps and Aſſociats the SEARCHERS:<note place="margin">Quàm iniquè comparatum ſit, videri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Reipub. <hi>Patres,</hi> ip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y; <hi>Vnlitas,</hi> quùm Quod opti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> iure, Optimis tantúm deſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſit, Munus: nunc tandem è Vulgi collu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie hominum Peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimis preſtituatur.</note> in the mideſt of a number of lawleſſe, hungrie, and for the moſt part ignorantly wilfull <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties,</hi> that like defectiue HETEROCLYTS, wrangle with the very rules of Grammer (pittying the <hi>Merchant</hi>) ſup vp their owne griefes, and bemoane themſelues in this maner.</p>
            <p>¶ That the meanes to enhable them to ſeruice, <hi>viz. Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> and <hi>Maintenance,</hi> are withholden from them and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred vpon others. That their ſeruice notwithſtanding is like the making of Bricke in <hi>Egypt,</hi> for wanting meanes to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their Taskes, yet haue idle <hi>Taske maſters</hi> ſet ouer them, whoſe credite hath no <hi>(being)</hi> but in their diſgrace.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
That the Lawe it ſelfe, ſo good and iuſt in generall, is made both hurtfull to the <hi>Prince</hi> in their publike function, and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to themſelues in their priuate callings. For that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they are preciſely enioyned at their admiſsions, and which in reſpect of their places and charges,<note place="margin">The Law is made to debarre Cuſtumers from their beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours.</note> they ſhould and might beſt performe; by one and the ſame way to the <hi>Princes</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate profit, which others at the ſecond hand haue made ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileable for themſelues: The <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> of all men are by ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute forbidden, namely, to meddle with any <hi>Trade</hi> or <hi>Traffick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That their ſeruice beſides is no thanks to themſelues, but a Countenance and meanes of Maintenance to others.</p>
            <q>Sic vos non vobis nidificatis Aues fertis aratra boues &amp;c.</q>
            <p>That <hi>They,</hi> notwithſtanding, vnderly all kind of Expences and hazards incident to Cuſtume cauſes, and others not tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the burden with their fingers, for crying ayme onely, reape thankes, reputation and reward. For (omitting extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinaries) their expences for their Bands and Suerties, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere al Duties &amp; ſubiection beſides, is an vnknowne bondage and burden, in reſpect of the libertie the reſt doe liue in.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Cuſtume-houſes built by the Prince in the Out-Ports.</note>
               <hi>They</hi> onely are to prouide, hire and furniſh for euery <hi>Porte</hi> of their charge a conuenient Cuſtume houſe, which beſides Tables, Deskes and neceſſaries fit for ſuch places, are hardly hired for 40. a peece of yerely rent, So as where (for examples ſake) there are fiue Portes;<note place="margin">he writers owne chardge in Kent. <hi>5.</hi> Portes.</note> for fiue Cuſtume houſes, the <hi>Cuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> is chargeable with the yearely rent. Of. 10. ot. 12.</p>
            <p>At each of theſe fiue <hi>Cuſtume houſes,</hi> muſt be intertained a diſcreete Perſon: for though any be fit enough for the <hi>Superui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> turnes (as matters doe ſtand) yet it ſtands the <hi>Cuſtumer</hi> in hand to vſe choiſe, and honeſt men of the beſt education (the ſeruice paſsing in Latine) for his owne ſecuritie. And vnto ſuch, leſſe then twentie markes wages, and as much for dyet cannot be offered. Which yearely is a charge of two hundreth pounds, or more. <hi>the Head-Porte conſidered in proportion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At theſe fiue <hi>Custume houſes,</hi> what euer is ſpent in Incke, Parchment, Paper, and Wax, is ſupplied alwaies by the <hi>Custu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> only, which yearely may be a Matter of ſome. 10. pounds.</p>
            <p>¶. Beſides. The hazard of the Queens money, that of neceſsitie is to paſſe by Bils of Exchange through ſundrie hands (being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed no <hi>Portage money</hi>) is an vnknowne hazard, trouble,<note place="margin">W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t of Portage m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ney.</note> and care to the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> onely, which the reſt breake no ſleepe for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theirs</hi> alſo are all charges, expended in ryding or ſending from place to place, as the ſeruice fals out by letters, or Order from the Lord Treaſurer or Exchequer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Laſtly, They put in their Bookes twiſe a yeare, to their dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble charges, which the reſt performe but once yearely, for faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſake onely, without expence or attendance, leauing the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> onely to abide to follow; and to pay all Duties, Fees, and whatſoeuer charges to <hi>Officers</hi> and others. Wherein the beſt part of their wages and reward from the <hi>Prince</hi> is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but vſually the one halfe, if not two parts of three, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more delayed, and accumbred with the confuſed entries, and writings of others Bookes, by careleſſe and ignorant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, then any of their owne, as the Auditors can witneſſe. Which kind of bondage of <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> the reſt in their freedome doe many waies inſult vpon, colouring their doings alwayes with the generall <hi>Pretence of her Maieſties ſeruice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all which expences both certaine and caſuall, the <hi>Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, Comptrollers,</hi> and <hi>Superuiſors,</hi> beare no part, each poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his life with libertie, his wages with quietneſſe, and his Trade with credite, and as it were altogether liue as they liſt. Whilſt the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> ouer-borne, and debarred all <hi>Trafficke</hi> and meanes of good ſeruice and thrift, are in caſe like the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant</hi> (aforeſaid) forced either to quit their places, though with loſſe,<note place="margin">Quod Neceſsitate cogitur, Neceſsitate defenditur.</note> or relieue themſelues as they may by one meanes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as <hi>Neceſsitie</hi> compels them. <hi>Extremities</hi> breeding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſhifts.</p>
            <p>¶ Hauing thus farre layd open the ſtate of the ſeruice, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to three of the fower Conſiderations afore laide downe) with the bondage and expences depending: Which (as appeares) the <hi>Custumers</hi> onely vnderly; there reſteth in a word or two, fourthly, to ſhewe the proportions of rewards, which alone being but indifferently weighed, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y happily helpe to excuſe them hereafter, though the age we liue in, giue ſmall hope of reliefe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fees and rewards for Seruice allowed by the Prince.</note>The <hi>Fees</hi> and <hi>Rewards</hi> yearely allowed by the <hi>Prince</hi> to the <hi>Custumers</hi> and <hi>Comptrollers</hi> ioyntly (the <hi>Searcher</hi> is allotted the moyetie of all ſeaſures) in all the OVT-PORTES of this Realme amount vnto the ſumme of 1240. little vnder or ouer, whereof the <hi>Comptrollers</hi> receiuing for their parts about. 340. the reſt being ſome 900. ſerues the <hi>Custumers</hi> among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This 900 deuided into three parts, two at the leſt are ſpent in paſsing, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending and clearing accompts. So reſts not aboue 300. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible among them, to recompence their bondage and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, being leſſe then the <hi>Comptrollers</hi> receiue with freedome and eaſe.</p>
            <p>A proportion very hard and vnknowne, but to thoſe that find it by experience, yet the ſame compared with the <hi>Superui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:877:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>(whoſe ſeruice and the <hi>Comptrollers</hi> is one and the ſame;) commes to a farre leſſe reckoning. For where the <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> being in number 20. deuide about 300. <hi>Deductis deducendis</hi> (as is aboue ſaid) among them all, and that vpon accompt at the yeares end. The <hi>Superuiſors</hi> being but. 4. receiue by <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur</hi> out of the Exchequer, (for their good ſeruice) 425. euery quarter,<note place="margin">1700. li. Yearely for no ſeruice at all.</note> which coms to 1700. yearely without accompt or reckoning.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cuſtumers ſtand cleared before God and the world, of the Princes offence, and all other ſlaunderous reports and ſuggeſtions againſt them and their calling.</note>By this time the VNDERSTANDING READER may diſcerne betweene <hi>eſt</hi> and <hi>videtur:</hi> and who is that Officer hath cauſe to complaine. And the <hi>Prince</hi> hath wherewith to bee ſatisfied in both the grounds of her diſpleaſure, at leaſt not to bee longer offended with the diſtreſſed <hi>Custumers.</hi> For by the Lawe of nature and Nations both <hi>Imputari non debet ei per quem non ſtat, ſi non facit quod per ipſum eſt faciendum.</hi> The reaſon is yeelded withall <hi>Quia culpa caret, qui ſcit, &amp; probibere nequit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>................................ ADSIT REGVLA, <hi>Peccatis qua poenas irroget aquas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ The <hi>Marchantes</hi> haue beene heard to ſay for themſelues. Now the COMMONS preſſe forward to ſpeake in their turnes, but they are too many and the time almoſt ſpent. Therefore heare but the PORT-TOVVNES, and reade their ſhort Petition.</p>
            <p>The life of all <hi>Cuſtumes</hi> is Trafficke and <hi>Commerce:</hi> In which kind of calling, the <hi>Merchant</hi> of all men is to be fauored, che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed; and incouraged in all Common-wealths.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Traffique</hi> is either <hi>Ourward</hi> or <hi>Inward,</hi> of things bread at home or abroad. And albeit that Kingdome or Countrie be holden moſt wealthie and happie, that is ableſt and apteſt to ſpare and tranſport Commodities of their owne, wherein this Iland may compare with the beſt; yet ſince no place is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſo abſolutely bliſt, as in all points to ſtand and ſubſiſt of it ſelfe, by the benefit of <hi>Entercourſe</hi> and <hi>Traffique,</hi> bounded by Lawes, <hi>Speciall treatiſe, Leagues, Oathes</hi> and <hi>Decrees,</hi> al wants are ſupplied, each Part intending the beſt for it ſelfe, according to Reaſon, Wiſedome and Pollicie. Which with vs heere in England hath euermore aymd at the encreaſe of our Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.<note place="margin">The encreaſe of the Nauie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This neceſsitie of mutual Commerce, by the malice of Time ſtands mightily enuied, and by Enemies abroad many wayes interrupted; if withall it become diſturbd among Equals at
<pb facs="tcp:877:14"/>home, when the generall is wrong, Particulars grieued cannot but grone.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aboundance and obſtructions diſtempering London, cauſe a diſpoſition to conſumption in all Portes beſides.</note>Such hath beene of late yeares, and yet is the State of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings &amp; Trades within our ſelues; for the Cittie of LONDON, as the Liuer in the body receiuing the <hi>Chylus</hi> from all parts of the Stomacke, by detaining the bloud from the reſt of the veines; is both inflamed &amp; diſtempered in it ſelfe, and iniurious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to all her fellow Members.</p>
            <p>In which eſtate, though the whole <hi>Commons</hi> ſeeme enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and deeply intereſſed (for it may bee the caſe of each pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Subiect) the <hi>Port-Townes</hi> in ſpeciall; conſiſting of <hi>Artificers</hi> and <hi>Traders, Maſters</hi> of <hi>Shippes</hi> and <hi>Mariners,</hi> doe moſt grieue and therefore complaine.</p>
            <p>That albeit as Subiects vnderlying the brunts of all forraine attempts and troubles,<note place="margin">The Out-Ports Complaint.</note> liuing vnder one and the ſame Lawes, ready at all commands of publike ſeruice by Sea &amp; by Land, as the other Subiects and Townes of the Realme are: And as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all duties and paiments of <hi>Cuſtumes, Subſidies, Fifteenes, Priuie ſeales, Loanes,</hi> &amp; ſuch like, yea as LONDON it ſelfe, is euery kind of way (for the proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their abilities) yet contrarie to the generall libertie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Subiects, they are abridged enuied, and as it ſeemes, helde<note n="a" place="margin">This hath relation to the ſtrange and vnnaturall courſes, holden in that Cittie, to drawe all dealings thither, debarring, and from hand to hand, by <hi>Tickets</hi> limitting things ſent into the Countries. As if all <hi>Citties, Townes</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> elſe where were but <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>burbes,</hi> All <hi>Portes</hi> but <hi>Creekes</hi> and <hi>Members,</hi> All <hi>Officers</hi> but Deputies depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on London, No <hi>Matter</hi> vendible, and ſo no <hi>Trafficke</hi> lawfull, but at, or for London. From whence as from the fatall Box of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora</hi> are flowne, and doe dayly proceede a great part of the euils, wherewith the whole Realme is become ſo perplexed. For thereby the free and lawfull <hi>Trafficke</hi> betweene equall Subiects, is violently impeached. <hi>Trades</hi> and <hi>Occupations</hi> in the Citties, and In-land Townes are generally decayed. Whereby the Commons empay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, grow diſcontented, and the poore for want of worke, forced out to begging. The skirtes and <hi>Out-Ports</hi> of the Realme grow dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly deſolate of <hi>Trades</hi> and deſtitute of <hi>Marriners</hi> and <hi>Shipping.</hi> The Princes <hi>Custumes,</hi> there conſequently decreaſed. The <hi>Cuſtumers</hi> without diſtinction by all meanes diſgraced. And the <hi>Marchantes</hi> of all ſortes diſcouraged, wearied and made a pray to a worlde of rauening and lawleſſe creatures, of whome, as of <hi>Harpies</hi> may be truely ſpoken.
<q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Virg.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <l>Triſtius haud illis Monſtrum, nec ſaeuior vlla</l>
                     <l>Peſtis &amp; ira Deum, Stygiis ſeſe extulit vndis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>No monſters like to theſe might hap, nor curſe from God befal</l>
                     <l>Nor from the pit of Hell ariſe, to plague a Realme withall.</l>
                  </q>
               </note>
VNWORTHIE, the very ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities of that Citties aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, to their manifeſt decay, (for want of free <hi>Trafficke</hi>) in their <hi>Inhabitants, Mariners</hi> and <hi>Shipping.</hi> And that all things being drawne into <hi>Priuate ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties,</hi> are there ſo ingroſſed, that ENGLAND is but LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON, and LONDON alſo ſeemes abridged in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>In which diſtreſſe the PORT-TOVVNES appealing in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie to the PRINCE, their onely comfort is, that albeit her Maieſtie as a Mother of all her Children in her<note n="a" place="margin">Sacred</note> 
               <hi>Loue</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Royall.</note> 
               <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> (as well may beſeeme Her) ſtand gracious to ſome more then the reſt:<note place="margin">A naturall &amp; liuely Similitude of the <hi>Princes</hi> PRERO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GATIVE</note> yet that her <hi>Storge</hi> and naturall inclination to <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> affords bread to the meaneſt, and intendeth at leaſt, that all ſhould enioy their birth-rights in the generall treatiſe of
<pb facs="tcp:877:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Entercourſe</hi> abroad, and <hi>Common Lawes</hi> at home, to growe vp thereby to liue to her Seruice and the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Let not LONDON therefore enuie her fellow Subiects to breath common ayre any longer, liuing vnder one and ſhee ſo good a SOVERAIGNE; nor diſgrace her fellow ſeruants of equall place and function, for the reaſons afore laide downe.</p>
            <p>And in LONDON more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>Societie</hi> of MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHANTS<note n="b" place="margin">The Argument of this Diſcourſe, being the <hi>Aduancement</hi> of <hi>Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumes,</hi> and the drift thereof, <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> to the <hi>Prince</hi> and her <hi>Kingdome:</hi> was reſolud at the firſt to depend efficiently on <hi>Trafficke.</hi> That <hi>Trafficke</hi> conſiſted of fower eſſentiall Parts or Pillers, <hi>Matter, Perſons, Place,</hi> and <hi>Order.</hi> That to maintaine Trafficke and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Cuſtumes, &amp;c. Was to procure and cheriſh in all Matter, <hi>Goodneſſe:</hi> in all Perſons, <hi>Loyaltie</hi> and <hi>Friendſhip:</hi> in all Places <hi>Conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie</hi> and <hi>Freedome:</hi> and in all Order generall <hi>Equitie,</hi> the beſt Rules whereof, were onely to be found in the <hi>Certaintie</hi> and <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie</hi> of the poſitiue <hi>Lawes, Treaties</hi> and <hi>Contracts</hi> of mutuall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce. But the <hi>Marchants Aduenturers,</hi> not knowing or not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe fower eſſentiall grounds together, run away with Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke, as if it ſtood onely in the choiſe of <hi>Perſons,</hi> and by their vneuen, vncertaine and violent proceedings, holde all men vnder to keepe themſelues aboue. Terming all <hi>Enterlopers</hi> that would liue by the direct and ſet Lawes of Trafficke, as if all were baſtards, and ſcarce good Chriſtians, at leaſt no <hi>Loyal Merchants</hi> nor <hi>Friends,</hi> but they and their <hi>Societie.</hi> And by a bare and idle pretence of the word <hi>Order</hi> and orderly tranſporting the <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Creame</hi> of the Land <hi>(Cloth)</hi> haue brought the Trade there of to a kind of confuſion, and themſelues to ſuch a Laborynth: that beſides the diſtreſſe of the <hi>(Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers)</hi> withall their Dependants, and generall complaints at home (to their Ho. Lordſhips endleſſe offence and trouble at the <hi>Councell Table</hi>) the Commoditie it ſelfe is impayred, abaſed and in a ſort deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the State withal dangerouſly deuided &amp; vnkindly at Iarre with her auncient <hi>Allyes</hi> and beſt forraine <hi>Friends.</hi>
               </note> ADVENTVRERS, that ſometime haue beene as curious to keepe and debarre men from their MART-TOWNS as now they ſeeme violent to force all men thither. Leaſt by their vnquiet and vncertaine <hi>Instruments</hi> and forme of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, they make good at home amongs themſelues and within themſelues, againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that, Straungers haue feared, written and foreſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <q>terming them a <hi>Priuate, Particular,</hi> and <hi>Preuenting</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ This is the ſtate of the CVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVMES, as they are at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, fit for the GRAVE and WISE to knowe and conſider. The reformation whereof, though none but <hi>Authoritie</hi> may promiſe and performe; yet common Dutie makes it lawfull in all to wiſhe and further. Vnto whome therefore in all <hi>Submiſsion,</hi> the PORT-TOVVNES for themſelues and their<note n="*" place="margin">Cities &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Townes of this Realm.</note> FRIENDS, by way of remembrance, doe make this Petition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>QVi Reipub. praeſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. Offic. li. 1.</note> 
               <hi>vt duo praecepta teneant. Vuum, vt vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem Ciuium ſic tueantur, vt quicquid agant, ad cam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferant, obliti commodorum ſuorum. Alterum, vt totum corpus Reipub. curent, ne dum partem aliquam tueantur, reliquas deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Qui autem parti conſulunt, partem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> negligunt, ſeditiones &amp; diſcordias inducunt. Ex quo fit, vt alij Populares, alij Optimi cuiuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſtudioſi videantur, pauci vniuerſorum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:877:15"/>
            <head>An abſtract or part of a Letter, written by Maſter <hi>Roger Askham</hi> (of moſt honeſt and learned memorie) from <hi>Auſpurge</hi> the xj. of Auguſt, 1551. vnto Maſter <hi>Leauer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A fit leſſon for London, and all Citties and incorporations in Englande, to preuent a Dearth by.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Agdeburge</hi> paſſeth the ſiege of Troy &amp;c. The prouiſion of Corne at <hi>Norenberge</hi> is notable. I wrote it to <hi>M. Cheeke</hi> and ſo I will to you, for I ſaw it. They haue eightéene ſtore houſes full of Wheate, whereof one flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was not taken vpon theſe (<gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>) yeares, as doth appeare in their Recordes and writings, yet the Wheate is good, it is ſo well kept.</p>
            <p>This prouiſion of Wheate maketh that Corne doth neuer fall nor riſe aboue twelue pence in a Quarter about <hi>Norenberge.</hi> For when a hard yéere commeth that Corne ſhould be déere among the Poore, then the Senate of <hi>Norenberge</hi> doe ſell to all that lacke plentifully at the olde price, and when Corne is ſo plentifull that the Poore men can get no money for it, then the Senate buyeth all that comes, and payes as much as the olde price was. Thus their Wheat except certain flowers is ſo renewed, that the people neither want Corne when it is deere, nor money when it is good cheape. They haue Lawes and Statutes for this good order. Such a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate be <hi>Veri Patres Reipub.</hi> God maintaine them, and giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers grace to follow them. &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:877:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
